<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/life/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-03-30T01:36:24+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/life/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">Swapneel Mehta | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Swapneel's Blog</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Student’s Guide to Living Abroad II</title>
      <link href="/a-students-guide-to-living-abroad-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Student’s Guide to Living Abroad II" />
      <published>2019-03-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/a-students-guide-to-living-abroad-II</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/a-students-guide-to-living-abroad-II">&lt;p&gt;This part is about the grind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the last post in a 2-part series. While the &lt;a href=&quot;/2018-07-10-a-students-guide-to-living-abroad-I&quot;&gt;first part&lt;/a&gt; highlights the preparatory phase, this post focuses on how life is different from what I expected when I first went abroad; it highlights the ups and downs based on a set of anecdotes and experiences.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-disclaimer&quot;&gt;The Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My primary motivation to write this article is to present a balanced view of both sides of the coin when it comes to living abroad. However, you will note that at certain points there is a certain amount of cynicism with which I look upon the conventional notions that (I believe) a significant proportion of my peer group (and myself at one point) subscribed to.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I write this article after having spoken at length (over the past year and a half) with a number of my friends that come from Indian universities and were accepted into the ‘top’ programs across the United States. I add to this my own experiences living and traveling in Europe. While this covers a significant portion of the target audience, I would agree with the claim that my dataset is limited and thus my arguments might be too specific; difficult to generalize at times. I will try my level best to keep the discussion general but over and above that, I trust the reader to make rational assumptions when extrapolating my arguments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This last disclaimer is mostly for when my parents call me up concerned about my mental health; I’d like to clarify that I’m quite happy and satisfied with where I am and I absolutely love the work I’m doing. However, this is mainly a result of the right combination of opportunities and luck. I fully recognize that this is not a combination that works out for everyone (or one that will continue to work out for myself in the future), and that is why I present this argument with a generous dose of cynicism at times, as opposed to painting a rosy picture of life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-prelude-and-a-regulatory-warning&quot;&gt;The Prelude and a Regulatory Warning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Freedom!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought when I stood facing the immigration counter at Mumbai airport, en route the next phase of my life in Geneva, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many Indians going abroad, I considered this my chance to be “independent” &lt;em&gt;(often synonymous with ‘wild and free’)&lt;/em&gt;. 
Freedom from the oversight of my parents; 
Freedom to spend &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; money where I want; 
Freedom to travel the world; 
essentially, freedom from the bucketload of socioeconomic constraints affiliated with the average ‘stay-at-home’ Indian student’s existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my head, I was planning all sorts of activities - I had travel plans lined up to Madrid, London, and South Africa. They were mainly machine learning summer schools; a combination of work and studies. Maybe that was why I didn’t give a second thought to the life that I was leaving behind and the people waving goodbye from the other side of the window at T2, Mumbai International Airport. Maybe I was so excited for what lay in store that I didn’t feel sad for what lay behind me as I headed into a jostling crowd of ‘foreign’-bound Indian aunties and uncles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone tells you leaving home is a life-changing experience; most stories conveniently omit the ‘hard’ bits of their experiences. Suddenly, you’re thrust into a world of possibilities. It could mean that you travel the city, meet new people, share new experiences, and try out new cuisines. This worldview meets with a counterview called ‘reality’ pretty soon. All these ‘new experiences’ sound pretty awesome until you realize that they could also mean you’re stranded on the tram stop at 1 am with no mobile network, as you squeeze your way out of the crowded bar of puking partygoers after a meal of tasteless, parboiled vegetables that constitutes a ‘traditional’ supper. Life is funny that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, I believe it is a great idea to be excited about new phases in life - temporary or permanent; good or bad. But on the other hand, it is unnecessary to have the wrong expectations of people and places you’ve never been to. A lot of my friends ended up getting an inaccurate idea of the responsibilities associated with moving abroad and they were more often than not in for a rude shock rather than a pleasant surprise. They seem to have coped well, but then not everyone is that lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In an era where ‘living my best life’ porn has hijacked the purpose of social media, I think it grows increasingly important to provide a reality check to counter this gold-plated fantasy people assume everyone else lives. Calibrating the right expectations &lt;em&gt;at least for the peer groups I am a part of&lt;/em&gt; is what I hope to achieve in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is as much a reflection of the experiences of my friends in the United States as it is an observation of life in Europe. Its suitability for extrapolation to life in other countries would depend on regiospecific patterns and nuances, but I hope some of the ideas I highlight can calibrate expectations on the right scale. For my part, I definitely believe I have had (and continue to have) a well-balanced life at CERN, but I concede there have been lows to match the highs. I will utilise these as anecdotes to highlight some common misconceptions that I had and how they impacted my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Of course, my opinion might be too cynical for many (including myself) to take seriously, but I hope the readers can make that distinction for themselves.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In retrospect, I emphasised the setting for this article twice (once in the disclaimer) but I feel in the current light of a blind mass-migration of Indian engineering graduates abroad this is a really critical point to drill in.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I left my home, my people, and my country behind in search of opportunities to launch a career as a computer engineer; full of an effervescent joy for the life that awaited me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am just another kid trying to make a living for himself and his family. I genuinely believe I am lucky to be on a path to make useful contributions in my line of work - artificial intelligence. Early on, I had a lot of vague ideas about ‘changing the world’ that eventually gave way to narrower, quantifiable, concrete goals within a ‘grand plan’. In fact, I have this ‘Book of Ideas’ that highlight some mind-numbingly awesome plans I came up with as a kid along with a commentary on the pros, cons, and obstacles for each. Funnily enough, some of these plans have already been “copied” by startups that are doing really well for themselves. But I take solace in the fact that this serves as validation - some of these crazy ideas actually had substance to them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to my goals, I’d get a bit technical here if I were to highlight specifically what I’d like to achieve when I say ‘change the world’ but I’ll save that for a more detailed post later on. For now, let’s just say that there are always tweaks and improvisations to this ‘grand plan’, but I am happy that I am somewhere in the vicinity of realizing it in the next decade or three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reality-check&quot;&gt;Reality Check&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think excitement comes naturally when we consider living abroad - exploring new cities, cultures; working or studying at elite universities and leading an Instagrammable existence. I was no different. It was a fantastic country to live in, wonderful friends that I already had, brilliant researchers on my team, and extremely supportive parents. What could possibly go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of my friends heading to the United States were similarly quite pumped about learning from top-notch faculty, engaging with a wonderful set of classmates, building a global network of professionals, and receiving opportunities to work at firms at the bleeding edge of the tech revolution that AI is leading. I think it was a fair set of ideals to bear in mind, but most of us were not prepared for the point at which the tsunami of reality hit us. Lectures were hard; assignments took a significant amount of time and effort eating into the major part of the day; classmates and roommates were not the most helpful, often creating issues when living together; and the job market was dismal given the sheer number of applicants for the same post, factors including the political climate, arbitrary hiring practices, and the role of plain old luck in acing a standard programming interview. It takes a bit of time to realize this world is not as glamorous as it is made out to be. It is rewarding, but only after months of hardwork, weeks of sleepless nights, and almost daily battles with annoying roommates. To be perfectly clear, these are a cumulative set of issues over a short period that affected the bunch of friends and people don’t have to deal with all of these at once (unless they get &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; unlucky). But these issues do crop up from time to time and it takes a nontrivial amount of effort to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finances&quot;&gt;Finances&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independence comes with its own set of freedoms and the freedom to manage your own finances is one of these. A lot of people heading into grad school underestimate the mental impact of having to pay back a loan has on a candidate that is going through the grind of assignments and exams on a daily basis. If you are like me, you are constantly reminded of the exchange rate whilst purchasing groceries at the local supermarket. They have all these sayings that really don’t make sense to you until you are thrust into situations where they apply. Managing finances reminded me of how responsiblities and freedoms were two sides of the same coin, and how real shit could get if I had been the sole breadwinner for my family. Sure, I was relatively lucky because I was generating a comfortable income, but had I been in a situation where I had no income but only expenditure I daresay I would be under considerable mental strain as well.  I cannot possibly fathom the amount of stress that one would have to deal with if one’s family depends on their future income - that’s real &lt;strong&gt;adulting&lt;/strong&gt; right there. It impacts work; it impacts studies; there is nothing you can do about it except hold on to the idea that you will eventually get a job and pay everything back. That will make all the sacrifices and risks worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;loneliness&quot;&gt;Loneliness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Solitude is a great place to visit until you realize nobody might be waiting for you back home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone likes the idea of having ‘me-time’ and the best part about living on your own is the ability to determing where to spend your time outside of the classroom/workplace. But on occasion, it also feels nice to have people around. This hits hard (at least initially) - particularly for those of us moving from a very active familial environment to a studio apartment living in a room with housemates who might not be around much. You move from constantly having somehting to do into an environment where you might actually have nothing to do for hours on end (unless you’re like me :P) - or at least nothing you’d rather do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loneliness hurts, and most of us are afraid to talk about it; afraid of seeming weak and desperate. In my opinion, it’s a factor for a lot of mental problems that people claim to suffer from. I’ve been there for a short while and it isn’t a great place. Luckily, I have friends who never let me feel lonely for really long (annoyingly lovable pricks), forcing me to speak with them, do something I enjoy (sketching, cooking, running) or simply go out and meet new people. Find yourself a friend circle that will help you stay strong, engaging with you when you need them while giving you some personal space otherwise. At the same time, reciprocate the favor and do make time if you feel your friend(s) need(s) you. Most people just need for you to be there on the other end of the line and they’ll handle the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;damage-control&quot;&gt;Damage Control&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like I’ve been a bit too serious throughout the post so I’ll share some lighter views before heading into the next part of the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Life is worth living, no matter what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all my claims of having developed a melancholic worldview, I think moving out of your home is a critical experience for moulding a wholesome personality. As we grow up, most of us mature into young adults (I didn’t). This maturing doesn’t come about on its own - it is a product of experiences (and bad ones matter more than good ones), learnings, principles, and practice. Living and studying abroad is a really fast-track way of achieving a ton of experiences in a limited time span. It teaches you lessons in a way nobody ever could have imparted the same ideas. I genuinely believe it’s worth a shot, for the right reasons, and in the right situations. Everyone isn’t immediately going to be able to move out of their houses, but if you ever get the opportunity, do try it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;travel&quot;&gt;Travel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best parts about living in a new city is that traveling anywhere even within the city is basically a vacation with very little travel time. Plus, you can make trips to friends in nearby cities which makes for a very active set of weekends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, at least during the semester, this isn’t going to work well mainly because the fatigue is often not worth the weekend of fun. Sure, if you can manage to make the time and you find it worth it then by all means go ahead. All I mean to say is that it varies with people and situations. On the whole, though, Spring Break and Winter Break make for wonderful week-long trips that result in a significant amount of Instagrammable content (for the future influencers reading this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adult-supervision&quot;&gt;Adult Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No more adult supervision because you’re the adults now. Oh… crap!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody is around to shout at you for coming home at 2:30 am anymore. No more lectures on how you’re missing out on umpteen health benefits because you don’t eat eggplant curry. Nobody around to check that you’re studying and not bingewatching Game of Thrones on the night before your exam (I &lt;em&gt;aced&lt;/em&gt; that exam, okay!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Indians with the typical familial restrictions on dressing, partying, drinking, or dating, this is a gold-mine of opportunities. I’ve had quiet, docile friends turn into alcoholic partygoers. That’s an exaggeration, to be fair, but my point is that this opens up the doors to a lifestyle most would never have access to if they continued to live around imposing families. You can now go out when you want, party as much as you’d like to, stop drinking milk (I’m surprised how much that comes up) and eating stuff you don’t like, watch movies late into the night, call your significant other over, maintain an active dating life, or whatever the heck you want. There is nothing to stop you save for the fear of consequences arising from poorly reasoned life choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, my parents aren’t controlling in any sense (and neither were most of my friends’ parents), but I do know of the occasional case where the kids lashed out at years of unhealthy restrictions by taking every opportunity they got to engage in activities that were not accessible to them before. It usually didn’t end well but those are a result of their decisions alone. So it’s a fine line between freedom and anarchy that is entirely dictated by the amount of responsibility one would decide to exhibit when ‘let loose’, so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-joy-of-living&quot;&gt;The Joy of Living&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Life is an uphill ride. Pedal hard, because you’re sitting on a bike with no brakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is going to be hard, but the fruits of your labor will be just as sweet. It is really cool to survive all these experiences. When you look back at the arduous path you took navigating a series of situations in the best manner you could, it feels really satisfying that you ended up where you did. For a change, mom cannot take as much direct credit (although she will try) for your success albeit their presence did make a critical difference everytime. You can actually feel happy about &lt;strong&gt;adulting&lt;/strong&gt; like a real adult, something that tells you you’re probably ready to grow slightly older and more mature than you were before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, I doubt I have grown any more mature than I was two years ago, but I have &lt;strong&gt;definitely&lt;/strong&gt; learnt a ton of vital lessons about living, loving, and losing. Obviously, as a professional I have developed far more than I would have imagined, courtesy a wonderful team and encouraging community. That would probably be another post at a later stage - highlighting how 2018 has been one heck of a rollercoaster ride. But I would say I genuinely enjoyed this journey and look forward to the next chapter starting later this year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;generalizing-the-arguments&quot;&gt;Generalizing the Arguments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have frequently used the term ‘abroad’ where I really mean to imply ‘away from home’. I realize now that the same arguments apply in situations where one moves to a new city albeit within the same country. For India, where cultural diversity varies drastically from region to region, moving to a new city may as well be equivalent to moving abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have utilised examples for both working and studying abroad and it should be noted that there are subtle differences between the two where I have painted the picture in broad strokes than would highlight these nuances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;life-in-switzerland&quot;&gt;Life in Switzerland&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switzerland, for the most part, is just plain wonderful. In comparison to many other countries, we have little crime, little poverty (if you’re poor and homeless, you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; can’t afford to live in Geneva), lots of mountains, valleys, rivers, and a big-ass lake. I spent a week traveling around with my family and can confirm it is, for the most part, composed of a charming and picturesque set of villages and towns with a dash of modernism added here and there. Swiss chocolates and cheese are renowned the world over and finally I can claim to understand why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I live in a village on the French side of the Franco-Swiss border called Saint-Genis Pouilly (‘saun-genie-poo-ey’) and bike down to the Swiss side where I work (yes, border crossing is chill out here). It’s cheaper, less travel, and closer to the beautiful Jura mountain range than the options I had available in Geneva. However, there are understandably fewer social events, gatherings, and parties in Saint-Genis if you’re new to the area as opposed to Geneva that actually possesses some semblance of nightlife. It isn’t as important initially, but this lack of socializing opportunities might get to some people later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The working week is about 40 hours, with some ups and downs based on your personal preferences. My team is pretty relaxed about how I manage those hours although I am usually at my office for about 8-10 hours a day. I also have side-projects and personal commitments that I work towards in the additional time I have. Evenings are usually meant to cook dinner, chill with my housemates (we recently realized we share a love for chess!), or simply watch a few episodes of Fresh Prince of Bel Air (I just started BoJack Horseman, though). Finally, on the weekends there are usually outings planned, parties to attend, places to be, or a few movies to watch. Incidentally, this weekend I’m spending on wrapping up some incomplete blog posts. I get enough time to spend on myself and I signed up for Taekwondo lessons at CERN about three months ago. Turns out CERN has everything from a finance club to a sailing club for its members to subscribe to. That makes it really convenient and affordable to find activities for your spare time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pros&quot;&gt;The Pros&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of pros to living in Switzerland: firstly, the standard of living is pretty high. You will be enjoying top-notch services wherever you go; discomfort is rare and usually addressed quickly. Next, the weather is pretty mild throughout the year. To be clear, there are rainstorms and snowstorms but the frequency of these and (judging by Mumbai standards) is really not much. The temparature reaches slightly under freezing on a bad winter day but it isn’t too bad to step out of the house, almost ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are mountains to hike up and valleys to ski down. Water sports open around the summer and adventure activities are aplenty. Geneva also has a lot of festivities around the few months of summer although it reduces around the winters. I had a lot of fun learning ice-skating this winter (two lessons and I can skate without falling), courtesy a friend who proved an encouraging mentor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, and most importantly, the crime rate is almost zero (if not zero). Like, there is literally no danger if you walk through the city unaccompanied at even 3 am in the night (I know because my friends and I have done this :P). Sure, there are some areas where it might be unadvisable to do this but for the most part, it is perfectly safe to hang out anywhere at any time. This has its advantages because living and traveling is much easier when you don’t have to worry about the safety of yourself and your belongings. Small things like if you have to visit the ATM at an odd hour, you don’t have to think twice about your safety which is not what I heard about many other cities around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-cons&quot;&gt;The Cons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a price to pay for everything and boy does Geneva take that adage seriously. It costs between 10 and 25 Swiss Francs ($12 - $28) to have a fairly decent meal and travel costs about $16 if I’m going to and from the city (passes make it cheaper in the longer run). I’m not the partying type but I have been to parties and I can confirm that booze is not cheap either, so if you like having a good time, be prepared to shell out for it. The price isn’t as much of an issue because most people here are also paid well to live in Switzerland (well, we aren’t paid as richly at the student level but it’s still a comfortable wage). But it takes a while to adapt to the cost of living (I know it did for some of my friends and myself).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main issue I faced coming in as an Indian student working in the summers versus working in a year-long contract was that the summers were all fun and frolic which didn’t serve as enough preparation for what comes later. The nature of the work environment at CERN is that most of us are temporary hires (‘temporary’ ranging from a few months to a few years). You barely get used to a certain set of friends and suddenly, people are leaving and you have a completely new peer-group to hang out with. In my case, it took a huge mental effort to convince myself to go out, attend parties, network and expand my friend circle. I’m not so much an introvert as plain lazy to engage in these activities but my housemates were really active in this sense, and the atmosphere even at home was quite lively most of the time. On occasion, they dragged me off to parties that ensured I maintained a healthy social life. I was fortunate enough to keep bumping into crazy friends (man, did we have good times!) but this always came with the regret that the time we had to hang out was finite. It was the only issue I ever had with life out here, but I also understand that they hire us in fixed-contract roles for a reason and it’s really not that bad to get to know new people from time to time. On the bright side, this ensures I have friends in most major cities around the world. That is pretty useful when you’re couch-surfing on vacation ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have attempted to provide a complete picture of life abroad as an Indian student. Sure, I write this in my limited experience and capacity but it’s a start and I hope to be able to expand on this as I move to the next stage of my career starting grad school in a new country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fully understand there might be biases that creep in and experiences that others might not share. I have tried to keep it rather broad bearing in mind the audience for this post and I hope you found parts of it relevant to your respective situation(s)!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swapneel Mehta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="life" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This part is about the grind.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Student’s Guide to Living Abroad I</title>
      <link href="/a-students-guide-to-living-abroad-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Student’s Guide to Living Abroad I" />
      <published>2018-07-10T00:00:00+02:00</published>
      <updated>2018-07-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
      <id>/a-students-guide-to-living-abroad-I</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/a-students-guide-to-living-abroad-I">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the first of a &lt;a href=&quot;/2018-12-21-a-students-guide-to-living-abroad-II&quot;&gt;2-part series&lt;/a&gt;. While this one is focused on making preparations for the travel, the next one will (hopefully) provide deeper insight into how life works and what to expect from the outside world based on my experience so far.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last summer, I told my mom that I’d be traveling to live in a new country: in this case, France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You will die of starvation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;She seemed supportive.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next few weeks were spent teaching me to avoid dying of starvation and it would seem mom made it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been through the process, I’ve got some tips and tricks to share for students going about this the first time around. I’ve tried to use broad strokes and avoid region-specific concerns but you can feel free to email me about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is meant to serve as a guideline for traveling like a beast — obtaining maximal efficiency with minimal luggage; learning the ropes of survival on 35kg of baggage allowance. It incorporates elements of preparedness for moving to a new house, living alone in a new city, with new people around. I’ll try to use examples of my own practices although, fair warning, I’m no expert and still need to sit on my bags to shut them. But at least I don’t have to haggle with the check-in crew for extra kilos anymore (I lied, I still do).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an Indian boy, especially a Gujarati (we’re known for our affinity with food), traveling abroad I honestly had one single concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How much of my kitchen can I possibly stuff into my luggage?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like it or not, it’s a trade-off between carrying that prized cardigan or a pack of freeze-dried paranthas (Indian flat-breads). In my case, I had about 35 kilos of luggage allowance, but evidently even two bags of 23kg are not enough for some whilst migrating to a new land. A lot of my rather affluent friends purchase additional luggage to transport a sizeable chunk of India along with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is basically me trying to tell you (and parents possibly concerned about your survival), “Chill out. You’ll live.”
(Not) Planning&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I traveled to Switzerland for a couple of months, I didn’t bother to plan. That’s a really bad idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last summer, I carried along a lot of stuff that I could actually have bought for cheaper in France/Switzerland compared to India. This included a truckload of clothes, some food items, and spices that I never ended up using. Let’s take a look at these items:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ready-to-drink Tea Mix: Unless you’re traveling extensively, you’re not going to need more than 5–7 single sachets of this mix. Usually, I prefer the normal way of boiling tea leaves with milk and that’s been replaced slowly by the fantastic coffee I get out here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Freeze-dried Food: My mother, after substantial research, painstakingly cooked 7 kilos of two different vegetable curries (Pav Bhaji and Mixed Veg.) and had them dehydrated into packs of food that I could then simply boil and eat. To be fair, it was a pretty useful item until I realized that I could actually cook. Then it became a really mundane meal and I kinda liked the fresh, hot, spicy (even shitty) food that I made, so quite a few packs were left unused by the end of my stay.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chilly Flakes and Oregano: These two Italian spices are used globally, so carrying huge packets, in my opinion, was not a great use of my limited luggage space.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Biscuits: Don’t waste your time and space trying to stuff five packs of Bourbon down your bag when we all know the first thing you’re going to do is buy Oreo in wholesale quantities once you land.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rice and Flour: A friend of mine wanted to carry along kilos of rice and flour. People eat both these items the world over, so please calm down and search for the nearest grocer. I can guarantee with absolute certainty you will be able to find affordably priced products nearby.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thermal Wear: Google the weather before traveling, and for heaven’s sake don’t go overboard with your woolens. If it’s a cold place, it’s very likely the stores nearby will stock cheap winter wear. Some of them have really great deals in the summer so buying in advance might save you dem moneys.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Socks: Amazon is everywhere. Amazon delivers the heavens to your doorstep. I carried along like twelve pairs of socks but I could just as well have bought them in France (or via Amazon France). Sure, they may be a little more expensive, but you could use the extra space to carry along spices that you might need more than the socks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toiletries: Travel packs are fine, but there’s really little use in carrying along bigger bottles of shaving gel, shampoos, soaps, etc. especially if it’s not medically necessitated.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clothes: Carrying your wardrobe along is a painstaking process, not to mention an expensive one in terms of baggage allowance. If you’re going someplace in the summer just take a look at the local shops, sales, and order online. In my case, the $100 I would spend on carrying an extra bag of clothes could be used to buy the same number/quality of clothes from local shops (H&amp;amp;M, Celio, etc.) in the summer sales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you know how that works, let’s move onto the actual planning that would help optimize your packing efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Packing is all about prioritizing what you need. Some things are vital, others just aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rule of thumb: Food is ubiquitous. People eat food everywhere. Don’t look so surprised, it’s true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I left, I had no clue what kind of food I’d rely on in Switzerland, so I did what anyone with half a brain (and little use for it) would do: I brought my kitchen with me. Every single spice I could lay my hands on, I stuffed into the bag. However, when I actually spent 15 minutes searching for alternatives once I arrived in Switzerland, I was able to find a decent set of brick-and-mortar Indian stores in pretty much every major city from San Francisco to Delft, and Boston to Geneva. Apart from that there’s online options available in the USA as well as Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did eventually end up ordering online via a store called Swiss Rasoi that gave us a decent discount since we found 4 other Indians and ordered products in larger quantities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pro Tip: They have a sale each month, email them about it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Of course the trade-off for buying this stuff abroad is that you pay a lot more than you would in India. But if you’re moving abroad for a longer duration, you’re going to have to bite the bullet at some point.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;planning-tips&quot;&gt;Planning Tips&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know thy City:&lt;/strong&gt; The internet is at your fingertips. Don’t just search for places, search for people already there. Ask for suggestions unabashedly. Figure out the hacks that can help you live an easier life; I don’t just mean free refills of soda at the local fast food joints.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know thy Weather:&lt;/strong&gt; Having knowledge of the kind of weather you are going into is very helpful because it can help you plan the kind of clothing you require. If you’re traveling in the summer, you can purchase winter clothes on sale, saving yourself copious amounts of both, cash and luggage allowance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know thy Locality:&lt;/strong&gt; Even within cities, it is often a diverse landscape and some neighborhoods may be better than others (also more expensive). If you’re traveling, try to use Google Street View to check out the locality, the local stores, and most importantly whether Amazon delivers to the ZIP code.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know thy Public Transport System:&lt;/strong&gt; A systematic public transport system is extremely crucial in saving your time and can help you figure out the feasibility of traveling to local stores. Most of the times, you will find that Google Maps offers a fairly accurate picture of the schedules and means of transport but this is not always the case. Try to figure out the apps that help track local bus, tram and train schedules and check your connectivity to assess how likely it is that you can shop for groceries daily/weekly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know thy Roommates:&lt;/strong&gt; I got lucky to find the best roommates ever. We cooked, cleaned, worked, and traveled together. Connecting with your roomies beforehand enables you to split essentials, manage your packing e.g. not everyone needs to carry that mini-pressure cooker or the same old bunch of spices. Besides, it helps to know you’re not living with serial killers. Mostly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know thy Telecom Providers:&lt;/strong&gt; International packs from India cost me between INR 2,500 and INR 4,000 and gives me maybe a hundred minutes of calling to India, a couple of gigs of internet and so on. A Freemobile (yes, it’s a company) costs me 25 Euro (~INR 1,600) and gives me 50–100GB of pan-Europe internet, and unlimited calling to international* numbers (including India). It’s always simpler if you know the plans in the country you’re moving to because eventually you’re going to be getting them anyway.
*maximum of 200 different phone numbers, but it’s still a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-visa-application&quot;&gt;The Visa Application&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I required a Schengen Visa for my work in Europe, but before that I was planning on attending school in the USA so I had an active F1-Visa that I later returned following the return of my I-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Schengen Visa permits travel within 26 countries situated in EU and Switzerland (Switzerland is not officially a part of the EU but for practical purposes, you don’t need to worry about it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This also means the Swiss use the Swiss Franc (CHF) and not the Euro. Some places accept both, but offer bad exchange rates for Euro to CHF conversion so you’re better off carrying CHF in advance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-swiss-schengen-visa&quot;&gt;The Swiss (Schengen) Visa&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Visa Application in India, VFS is a courier company that collects your application and biometric details and sends it off to the Swiss Embassy in New Delhi. Some tips for the application for the Swiss Visa:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be clear about your Visa-type. For students, it’s usually the &amp;lt;90-day Visa or for longer stays (e.g. 1 year), the Type D National Visa (at least at CERN).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on the Visa-type there are checklists available for the supporting documents required. Go through these thoroughly before doing anything else. Read a few different checklists if you’re like me and want to get a better idea of what you might need (even though you really won’t).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Preferably book an appointment 6+ weeks before your travel dates. It barely takes a few days for your Visa to arrive but having a buffer period is safer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In some cases, you need to get a bank statement verified by an official that shows you have some funds to sustain your lifestyle. For most banks this takes a few days so get it done early on.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get your bookings in order; especially residence. You can use Booking.com or Hotels.com for at least a temporary accommodation solution until you finalize the details of your stay. I booked my return-trip flights in advance but I’ve been told it’s not mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not a very “stringent” procedure because it’s not “an interview” — as per my understanding, VFS acts as an intermediary, and is supposed to help you out with preparing your application for the Schengen Visa. So no need to be nervous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US Visa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my F1 Visa Application, I have a vague recollection of the procedure so I’ll be brief; please confirm these details before proceeding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It had (understandably) a far more detailed application form than the Schengen Visa. They asked me about all the times I had visited the USA in the past and I had to dig up my expired passports to look up the exact dates.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They require an I-20 if you’re applying for the F1 or (if I’m not mistaken) J1 Visa. The I-20 must also be presented at the time of arrival in the USA (at immigration).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here, the fees are to be paid online and cost me somewhere around $160 (INR 10,000) at the time of application.
There are two separate appointments: one for collecting your biometric details and another for the actual “interview.” Yes, this is an actual interview and if you do not answer to their satisfaction, they reserve the right to refuse your Visa without justification.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As per what I have seen and heard, your finances matter here. I can’t offer any “magic combination” to pass all scrutiny but simply be clear about what you are saying and avoid falsifying information at all costs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have a hunch that your institute matters because I was going only for a summer but I was given a 5-year F1 Visa. My I-20 was from a highly reputed institute so maybe that made life much easier for me. Or maybe I just got lucky (although I ended up returning the I-20 and Visa).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;flight-selection&quot;&gt;Flight Selection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Booking flights isn’t always about getting the cheapest travel option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, it mostly is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a student, it is easy to just go for the cheapest options but if you’re looking to go a little deeper think about it this way: if you travel smart, the more you travel, the cheaper it gets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So a slightly more expensive flight option now will get you not only more comfort and luggage allowance now but also help you improve your traveler status and increase the probability of free upgrades in the future.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will avoid going into details but you can read more about airline alliances that comprise of 3 major groups of airlines that allow you to earn miles when you fly any of them in the same group. Later you can redeem them for vouchers, discounts, and of course free flights. Alliances also have tie-ups with some credit card companies and car rental services to help you earn free miles so take a closer look and maybe you’ll find yourself traveling business class on a free upgrade before the end of the decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important factor is to request student status, a provision most carriers offer. At the very least you get extra luggage allowance, but sometimes you might get good discounts. Student tickets are often non-refundable so ensure that you’ve got a solid plan in place before finalizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pro Tip: If you travel like I do (overfilled luggage; prepared to haggle at check-in counters), it helps to transfer most of your weight to the ‘laptop bags’ or ‘purses.’ They have never bothered to ask me about the big-ass laptop bag I carried with me (I travel Emirates, in case you’re wondering).
Update: Based on a friend’s experience, Etihad did charge them for extra kilos at Abu Dhabi. Avoid pushing your luck.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;layovers&quot;&gt;Layovers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to be very excited about flights (note the past tense). The first time I booked my trip from India, I picked a Lufthansa flight to Geneva with a 9-hour layover in Munich because why the heck not!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a plan, and a backup plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-plan&quot;&gt;The Plan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will take the Lufthansa shuttle into Munich and then figure out where I can travel around. I never looked into the places I could visit — I would have data or at least free WiFi and I could figure it out.
The Backup Plan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Munich airport is rated 2nd in the World. It has a mini-golf course and a spa, among other amenities. It costs about 6CHF which is decent. Worst case, I play 9 hours of mini-golf. Not a bad way to spend the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reality&quot;&gt;Reality&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data pack was inactive. No network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“No problem, I have free WiFi.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WiFi isn’t connecting and there’s nobody around that speaks English to help. In fact, there’s literally nobody around except a few security guys and cleaning staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s alright lets skip the city shuttle and enjoy the mini-golf and spa.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It’s a Saturday morning. The activities are in another terminal and that’s shut for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Fuuu…..”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, that happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eventually I managed to figure out the location of the shuttle stop at the airport and reach the city center. A kind stranger bought me a train ticket and I roamed around some park; I still don’t remember the name. I ate at an Indian restaurant handled by jovial Pakistani dudes (it’s way more common than you’d think). Turns out the city is pretty lively towards the afternoon and I was served some crappy Lebanese brunch (“Sir, your vegan food”) whilst strolling around the farmer’s market before heading back to the airport. Pretty great layover overall, but things could have gone very wrong that day.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;planning-done-right&quot;&gt;Planning Done Right&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second time I traveled to Geneva, I was a seasoned veteran of air-travel (mostly just in my head though).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still ended up over-packing, rearranged my baggage at check-in, haggled with the personnel, and successfully managed to carry the other half of India into Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time around, I was more aware of what I should carry along and the items that had most helped the past summer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cash: It isn’t really necessary in the USA since most stores accept card payment, but in some places around France we still are required to pay in cash so it becomes necessary to carry sufficient cash or find an ATM assuming you have low fees for international withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Universal Travel Adapters: Mostly due to my Macbook (USB-C ftw), but also travel adapters are mighty useful to have in general. They can get pretty expensive to buy on airports or souvenir shops so be sure to carry a spare.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Essential Spices (bare minimum):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Chaipatti (Dried, Crushed Tea Leaves);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Red Chilly Powder;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dhanajiru (Cumin + Coriander Powder);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Turmeric;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Jeera (Cumin);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rai (Mustard Seeds);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hing (Asafoetida);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Chaat Masala;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Garam Masala;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pro Tip: you get sugar, pepper, and salt literally everywhere, including the airplane!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced Cooking (bare minimum):
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Poha (Rice Flakes);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Biryani Masala;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pav Bhaji Masala;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Aamchur (Dry Mango Powder);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Gud (Jaggery);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Imli (Tamarind);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tejpatta (Bayleaf);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elaichi (Cardamom);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Laung (Cloves);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dalchini (Cinnamon);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Kali Mirch (Black Pepper).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Namkeen: You don’t always have time to shop so keep some ready-to-eat food handy just in case you need it:&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Maggi, always;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Haldiram’s Poha.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ready-made Food Mix: Basically these are powders that you can use for various purposes without much effort:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;MTR Dosa Mix;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;MTR Upma Mix;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Talod Dhokla Mix.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vacuum-sealed Stuff: The first time I went, mother made some rotis, theplas, and paranthas (different Indian breads) at home and had them vacuum-sealed at the local grocer. It lasted around 2 months since I put it in the freezer immediately once I reached France. It’s a temporary hack, but it works. She also made me a minced chilly mix that I didn’t use as much but was helpful when we ran out of green chillies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cooking Appliances: The Pressure Cooker is infinitely useful. It is indispensable unless you have enough time to spend in the kitchen boiling rice and potatoes in a pan (this doesn’t take as long as you’d imagine). Get a small one along, it is worth the effort. I tried to carry a Roti Maker this time but unfortunately when I tried it out, the voltage shorted it. Sucks. But I can make roti without a roti-maker (that’s a lie, I’m too lazy). Okay fine, I will try again and update this post. Next, there’s the Pav Bhaji masher — I’m unaware of its exact name but hopefully you get what I mean. Finally, carry a good thermos along for the daily beverage or simply hot water, if you can spare the luggage space for it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Old Passports: If you intend on traveling to multiple countries, some places ask about your travel history for the Visa Application. It isn’t mandatory, but it helps if you have your older (even expired) passports to carry along.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Driving License: One big plus is that if you can drive in India, you can drive pretty much anywhere (in theory). Your license is valid between 6 months to 1 year, but it is advisable to get an international license made because it’s much cheaper in India. It’s amazing how empty the roads are, but ensure you know the road rules. Parking spots are a pain to find and more importantly understand. Fines are hefty. Also, don’t drink and drive. You can’t afford it. It’s that simple.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Photocopies of Documents: At the office, I can take free printouts. But outside, photocopies aren’t priced at a rupee for a side. Carry attested/sealed copies of at least your mark-sheets, passport, and Visa in case it is required on short-notice.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Passport-sized Photographs: Carry about thirty. I’m not kidding; Schengen requires a different format from the standard passport-sized photographs. Get the standard as well as Schengen-format photos printed so that you save time and effort spent on getting them made abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Munchies are awesome. Food here is bland, and most of my junk food comprises chips. “Mobile” Khakhra (Roasted flatbread) is a welcome break when I’m too lazy to get snacks at the cafeteria. Mother dearest found me packs of kurmura (puffed rice flakes) I wish I’d carried Soya Sticks but I believe it should be available at the local Asian store. 
&lt;strong&gt;Update: it was not :(&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Energy Bars: They’re available in a range of varieties at almost all grocerie sand they’re extremely easy to carry around. I have 2 in my bag at all times. Usually I prefer to buy them from abroad instead of carrying them from home. But it works either way. Nature Valley is decently priced if you buy the larger packs off Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parachute Coconut oil (small bottle): Easiest remedy for dry hair after days of daily shampooing. Honestly. Silky Smooth Amazeness.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Toiletries: While most of these are unnecessary in large quantities, you would do well to carry the tongue cleaner. It’s pretty useful if you don’t find a toothbrush that fits the bill. Seriously. Also nail-cutters; tiny, but very useful once every two weeks (that’s what she said). As a cleanliness freak, I carry a hand sanitizer wherever I go. I just have to.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Backpack: Invest in a sturdy, light-weight backpack that can be useful on both a regular basis as well as weekend trips. Nobody likes lugging suitcases around. You could figure out decent options once you arrive in case you’re aware of good sales. I know for a fact France has great offers during the summers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Electronics: If you don’t like spending a lot on electronics, carry a decent set of headphones, extra USB cables, and universal adapters. I like to exercise so bluetooth headphones are a necessity. For backups and other data storage. It could actually be cheaper to purchase hard drives in flash sales (or holiday sales) abroad, but we all know the sources of the ‘data’ that you need are of questionable legality outside the country so you’re going to bring one along anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shoes: If you’re going to indulge in adventure activities please bear in mind that healthcare costs skyrocket pretty easily. If you’re covered by insurance, that’s fine. But since I started play squash, football, and running, I’ve spent a bit of money on good quality running shoes that enable me to run on concrete without the jarring impact to my knees. I’m still dicey on skiing though.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pack of Cards: Monopoly Deal, Uno, plain old playing cards; try to stuff in whatever you can once you’re done packing the important stuff. Extremely useful when you decide to travel around with your friends and have nothing to do once you’ve uploaded 1500 snap-stories from the car/train/hotel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that covers pretty much all of the basic items you’d require to survive comfortably in a new environment. I’ll update the post with relevant information over time. But for now, good luck preparing for your travels!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swapneel Mehta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="life" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This is the first of a 2-part series. While this one is focused on making preparations for the travel, the next one will (hopefully) provide deeper insight into how life works and what to expect from the outside world based on my experience so far.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
